Guide to the Leo Bogart Papers, 1912-2010 and undated RL.10146
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Leo Bogart papers
1912-2010 and undated
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Bogart, Leo
RL.10146
62.0 Linear Feet
Leo Bogart was an applied sociologist and mass media expert who was Vice President and General Manager of the Newspaper Advertising Bureau (NAB) from 1960-1989. In his career with the NAB, Bogart pioneered new methodologies in newspaper marketing research and led two major projects during the mid 1970s-1989 to bolster the ailing newspaper industry, the Newspaper Readership Project and the Future of Advertising Project. He was also a prolific author and public speaker, and published 195 articles and 14 books, and delivered over 150 speeches from 1943-2005. The Leo Bogart Papers span the years 1912-2010 and document Bogart's professional work with the Newspaper Advertising Bureau; as a mass media expert; and as an author and public speaker. The collection includes correspondence, clippings, articles, speeches, books, journals, chapters, drafts, proposals, notes, reports, scrapbooks, resumes, interviews, schedules, programs, pamphlets, administrative records, research materials, publications, promotional materials, ephemera, yearbooks, student papers, military records, photographs, negatives, and slides. Materials represent Bogart's professional work as Vice President and General Manager of the Newspaper Advertising Bureau, as well as his early employment with Standard Oil (New Jersey), McCann-Erickson, and Revlon, Inc.; as a prolific author and public speaker; as a Senior Fellow with the Gannett Center for Media Studies at Columbia University; and as a mass media consultant with the Innovation International Media Consulting Group. The bulk of files relate to research on U.S. markets, although some files do cover international research projects. Topics include newspaper marketing research; newspaper readership; newspaper advertising; television and society; critiques of mass media; social science research methodology; and international newspapers in emerging markets. The collection also documents Bogart's early experiences as a student and as a soldier in the U.S. Army Signal Corps during World War II, which formed the basis for several of his writing projects.
Access Restrictions
Collection is restricted.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
In addition, original audiovisual materials are closed to patron use. Some use copies are available in the collection. Otherwise, Technical Services staff need to produce use copies before contents can be accessed.
Also, all or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Leo Bogart Papers were received by the Rare Book, Manuscript, and Special Collections Library as a transfer in 2005. Additional accessions were recieved as gifts in 2006, 2007, 2014.
Biographical Note
Chronology List
1921 Sep. 23 Born in Lvov, Poland
1923 Moved to the United States
1938-1941 A.B., Brooklyn College
1942-1946 Served in the U.S. Army Signal Corps in WWII
1946-1948 M.A. in sociology from University of Chicago
1947-1948 Instructor in English, Illinois Institute of Technology
1948 Aug. 8 Married Agnes Cohen
1948-1951 Opinion Research Analyst, Standard Oil Company (New Jersey)
1948-1950 Ph.D. in sociology from University of Chicago
1949-1951 Lecturer in Sociology, New York University
1951-1952 Fulbright Research Fellow, Institut National d'Etudes Demographiques, Paris, France
1952-1958 Vice President, Market Planning Corporation Division, McCann-Erickson, Inc.
1953-1961 Lecturer in Sociology, Columbia University
1956-1957 President, Radio-Television Research Council
1958-1960 Director of Marketing Research, Revlon, Inc.
1960-1966 Vice President of Marketing Planning and Research, Newspaper Advertising Bureau (NAB)
1965-1966 President, World Association for Public Opinion Research
1965-1966 President, Market Research Council
1966-1967 President, American Association for Public Opinion Research
1966-1989 Executive Vice President and General Manager, NAB
1971-1972 President, Consumer Psychological Division, American Psychological Association
1989-1990 Senior Fellow, Gannett Center for Media Studies, Columbia University
1990 Adjunct Professor of Marketing, New York University
1996-2005 Director and Senior Consultant, Innovation International Media Consulting Group
2005 Oct. 15 Died, Mt. Sinai Hospital, New York, NY
Organization Abbreviations
AAAA - American Association of Advertising Agencies
AAPOR - American Association for Public Opinion Research
ABC - Audit Bureau of Circulations
ACR - Association for Consumer Research
AEJ - Association for Education in Journalism (changed to AEJMC)
AEJMC - Association for Education in Journalism and Mass Communication
AMA - American Marketing Association
ANA - Association of National Advertisers
ANPA - American Newspaper Publishers Association
APA - American Psychological Association
APME - Associated Press Managing Editors
ARF - Advertising Research Foundation
ASA - American Sociological Association
ASNE - American Society of Newspaper Editors
ESOMAR - World Association of Opinion and Marketing Research Professionals (formerly European Society for Opinion and Marketing Research)
IAMCR - International Association for Media and Communication Research
IAPA - Inter American Press Association
ICMA - International Circulation Managers Association
IFRA - [publishers]
INAE - International Newspaper Advertising Executives (changed to INAME)
INAME - International Newspaper Advertising and Marketing Executives
INCFO - Institute of Newspaper Controllers and Finance Officers
INPA - International Newspaper Publishers Association
MRDA - Media Research Directors Association
NAB - Newspaper Advertising Bureau
NRMA - National Retail Marketers Association
WAPOR - World Association for Public Opinion Research
Collection Overview
The Leo Bogart Papers span the years 1912-2005 and document Bogart's professional work with the Newspaper Advertising Bureau; as a mass media expert; and as an author and public speaker. The collection includes correspondence, clippings, articles, speeches, books, journals, chapters, drafts, proposals, notes, reports, scrapbooks, resumes, interviews, schedules, programs, pamphlets, administrative records, research materials, publications, promotional materials, ephemera, yearbooks, student papers, military records, photographs, negatives, and slides. Materials represent Bogart's professional work as Vice President and General Manager of the Newspaper Advertising Bureau, as well as his early employment with Standard Oil (New Jersey), McCann-Erickson, and Revlon, Inc.; as a prolific author and public speaker; as a Senior Fellow with the Gannett Center for Media Studies at Columbia University; and as a mass media consultant with the Innovation International Media Consulting Group. The bulk of files relate to research on U.S. markets, although some files do cover international research projects. Topics include newspaper marketing research; newspaper readership; newspaper advertising; television and society; critiques of mass media; social science research methodology; and international newspapers in emerging markets. The collection also documents Bogart's early experiences as a student and as a soldier in the U.S. Army Signal Corps during World War II, which formed the basis for several of his writing projects.
Collection Arrangement
The collection is organized into six series: Personal Series; Professional Series; Photographs and Slides Series; Artifacts; Oversize Materials; and Audiovisual Materials.
The Personal Series consists of correspondence, clippings, fiction and nonfiction writings, notes, student papers, brochures, pamphlets, ephemera, drawings, yearbooks, scrapbooks, awards, military documents, photographs, and memorabilia that document Bogart's personal life. Series is divided into two categories: Student materials and Other materials.
The Professional Series consists of correspondence, clippings, articles, speeches, books, journals, chapters, drafts, proposals, notes, reports, scrapbooks, resumes, interviews, schedules, programs, pamphlets, administrative records, research materials, publications, promotional materials, and photographs that document Bogart's professional career. Series is divided into nine subseries: Biographical Materials Subseries; Conferences and Meetings Subseries; Correspondence Subseries; Early Career Subseries; Late Career Subseries; Newspaper Advertising Bureau (NAB) Subseries; Professional Service Subseries; Research Files Subseries; and Writings and Speeches Subseries.
The Photographs and Slides Series consists of photographs, slides, and negatives that document Bogart's personal and professional life. Photographs chiefly document professional meetings and conferences. Slides, which make up the bulk of this series, include Newspaper Advertising Bureau presentation slides; Freedom Forum Russia workshop slides; and family vacation and travel slides.
Artifacts consists of plaques and other awards.
Oversize Materials consists of large-format materials removed from other series.
Audiovisual Materials consists of videocasttes, DVDs, audiocassettes, CDs, and floppy disks, featuring or collected by Bogart. Many of the videocassettes were used for Bogart's work as a mass media expert in two trials, Chandler v. Jackson (Michael Jackson child molestation lawsuit) and Valenzuela v. Hughes Aircraft Company (TCE groundwater contamination lawsuit in Tuscon, Arizona).
In addition, approximately 110 computer discs were removed from the collection and stored on an electronic server (M:\Processed\Bogart, Leo). The majority of electronic files consist of articles, drafts, chapters and presentations that duplicate materials housed in the collection in paper form.
Related Material
Materials related to this collection may be found in the following Hartman Center collections of the J. Walter Thompson Company Archives: the Rena Bartos Papers; the Chicago Office Records; the Chicago Office Non-Proprietary Research Records; the Eleanor Newman Papers; and the Norman H. Strouse Papers. In addition, related materials may be found in the American Association of Advertising Agencies Records; the John Benjamin Harris Papers; the McGraw-Hill Marketing Information Center Vertical File; and the Walter Weir Papers.
Clippings (information artifacts); Negatives (photographs); Advertising, Newspaper -- United States; Marketing research; Marketing research -- United States; Mass media and culture -- United States -- History -- 20th century; Brochures; World War, 1939-1945 -- Personal narratives, American; Television -- Social aspects; Technology and society -- History -- 20th century; Machine-readable records; Ephemera; Slides (photographs); Photographs; Newsletters; Memorabilia; Speeches; Scrapbooks; Readership surveys -- United States; Popular culture -- United States; Sociology -- Research -- United States; Sociology -- Research; Mass media -- Audiences -- Research; Mass media and public opinion; Newspaper reading -- Research; Mass media -- Social aspects -- United States; Innovation International Media Consulting Group; Gannett Center for Media Studies; Bogart, Leo; Revlon, inc.; Newspaper Advertising Bureau (New York, N.Y.); McCann-Erickson Worldwide; John W. Hartman Center for Sales, Advertising & Marketing History; Standard Oil Company
- Personal Series, 1912-2002 and undated, 5 boxes
  Scope and Contents note
  Consists of correspondence, clippings, fiction and nonfiction writings, notes, student papers, brochures, pamphlets, ephemera, drawings, yearbooks, scrapbooks, awards, military documents, photographs, and memorabilia that document Bogart's personal life. Series is divided into two categories: Student materials and Other materials.
  Student materials consists of materials accumulated by Bogart over his student career at P.S. 99 Junior High School; Erasmus Hall High School; Brooklyn College; and the University of Chicago. Materials include student assignments and papers and materials relating to Bogart's work as editor-in-chief of Vanguard, a student paper of Brooklyn College.
  Other materials includes clippings on topics of personal interest to Bogart; fiction writings; and materials documenting Bogart's military service as a voice interceptor in the U.S. Army Signal Corps from 1942-1946. Lengthy fiction writings include The Temple of Janus, an unfinished sociological novel that Bogart developed for a writing competition, and The Argument. Several of Bogart's published writings were based in part on his experiences in the U.S. Army, including the article Soldier Thinking (1943) and the books Social Research and the Desegregation of the U.S. Army (1969) and How I Earned the Ruptured Duck: Behind the Lines in WWII (2003), which may be found in the Writings & Speeches Subseries. Arranged alphabetically.
  - Student materials, 1912-1970 and undated
    - Brooklyn College (Box 1)
      - Academic writings, 1938-1941 and undated (Box 1)
      - Class notes, circa 1938-1941 (Box 1)
      - Programs, 1937-1941 (Box 1)
      - Student newspaper articles, 1938 (Box 1)
      - Vanguard materials
        - Correspondence, 1938-1940 (Box 1)
        - Student politics, circa 1938-1941 (Box 1)
        - Writings, 1940-1941 (Box 1)
    - Comic sketches, 1931-circa 1940 (Box 1)
    - Correspondence, 1937-1946 and undated (Box 1)
    - Cover letter and biography, 1938 and undated (Box 1)
    - Ephemera, 1936-1937 and undated (Box 1)
    - Erasmus Hall High School
      - The Arch yearbook, 1937 (Box 1)
      - The Erasmian journal, 1935 (Box 1)
      - Newspaper and journal writings, 1936-1937 (Box 1)
      - One Hundred and Twenty-Fifth Anniversary Celebration: History of the School, Book of the Pageant, Commemoration Exercises, 1912 (Box 1)
      - Programs, 1937-1938 (Box 1)
      - Scrapbook, 1935-1937, 2 folders (Box 1)
      - Sesquicentennial celebration, 1937 and undated (Box 1)
    - Languages, 1936-1938 and undated (Box 1)
    - Letters of recommendation, 1937-1948 (Box 1)
    - P.S. 99 Junior High School
      - Essays, 1932-1933 (Box 1)
      - Spirit of 99 journal, 1929-1930 (Box 1)
    - University of Chicago (Box 2)
      - Academic writings
        - Academic papers and writings, 1946-1948 and undated, 3 folders (Box 2)
        - Bibliographies, notes and drafts, circa 1946-1948 (Box 2)
        - Master's thesis draft, The Response of Jews in America to the European Jewish Catastrophe, 1941-1945, circa 1948 (Box 2)
        - Ph.D. dissertation draft, The Comic Strips and Their Adult Readers: A Study of Male Workers in a New York City Neighborhood, circa 1950
          - Abstracts, 1950 (Box 2)
          - Correspondence, 1955-1970 and undated (Box 2)
        - Thesis and dissertation proposals, 1947-1948 (Box 3)
      - Convocation program, 1948 (Box 3)
      - Diplomas, 1948-1950 (Box 3)
      - Report on the Oil Workers Leadership Training Program, circa 1948 (Box 3)
      - Research projects, 1948 and undated (Box 3)
    - Writings by others
      - Scholars who influenced Bogart, 1941-1998 (Box 3)
      - Other writings, 1942-1947 (Box 3)
  - Other materials, 1937-2002 and undated
    - Agnes Bogart materials, undated (Box 3)
    - Articles by others, 1965-1988 (Box 3)
    - Awards and certificates, 1945-1989 and undated (Box 3)
    - Birth certificate (translated from Polish), 1941 (Box 3)
    - Children, 1977-1997 and undated (Box 3)
    - Clippings
      - Comics, 1950-1980 and undated (Box 3)
      - General, 1952-2001 and undated (Box 3)
      - People, 1987-1989 and undated (Box 3)
      - September 11 attacks, 2001-2002 (Box 3)
      - Travel and tourism, 1987-1997 and undated, 2 folders (Box 3)
    - Correspondence, 1950-1998 and undated (Box 3)
    - Ephemera, 1942-1992 and undated (Box 3)
    - Military service
      - Army administrative correspondence, 1943-1952 (Box 3)
      - Army discharge papers, 1946 (Box 3)
      - Army specialized training certificates and transcript, 1943-1946 (Box 3)
      - Clippings and memorabilia, 1938-1948 and undated (Box 3)
      - 'Dans l'Honneur et la Dignité': Souvenirs de Vichy booklet, 1945 (Box 3)
      - Holocaust and Nazi Germany materials, 1980-1994 (Box 4)
      - Journals and correspondence, 1944-1945 and undated (Box 4)
      - Signal Corps documents 1944-2002 (Box 4)
      - Veterans application for education benefits, 1946 (Box 4)
    - Notes, undated (Box 4)
    - Travel
      - Clippings and ephemera, 1987-1997, 2 folders (Box 4)
      - India trip, 1996 (Box 4)
      - Maps and itineraries, 1984-1985 and undated (Box 4)
    - Visual arts materials, 1980-2001 and undated, 2 folders
      - [Art prints, undated: Removed to Box 95 ] (Box 4)
      - [Cartoons, undated: Removed to Box 95] (Box 4)
      - [Drawing by Michele Bogart, 1962: Removed to Box 95] (Box 4)
      - [L'Illustration, no. 370, 1926: Removed to Box 95] (Box 4)
    - Writings
      - Argument manuscript, circa 1945 (Box 4)
      - Humor, 1967-1996 and undated (Box 4)
      - Short fiction, circa 1938-1942 (Box 4)
      - Short nonfiction, 1940-1942 and undated (Box 5)
      - The Temple of Janus manuscript
        - Background materials and correspondence, 1937-1941 and undated (Box 5)
        - Character synopses and manuscript notes, 1939-1941 (Box 5)
        - Chapters
          - Arnold Cohen, circa 1938-1940 (Box 5)
          - Betty Levine, 1939 and undated (Box 5)
          - Doris Greenberg and Julius Stiletsky, 1939 and undated (Box 5)
          - Douglas Churchill, 1939-1940 and undated (Box 5)
          - Ellen Menkin, 1939 and undated (Box 5)
          - Emma Daly, 1940 (Box 5)
          - Henry Selver, circa 1938-1940 (Box 5)
          - Herb Brenton, circa 1938-1940 (Box 5)
          - Judah Benjamin, 1940 and undated (Box 5)
          - Milton Steckler, circa 1938-1940 (Box 5)
          - Sam Daly, 1938 and undated (Box 5)
          - Selma Lober, 1939 and undated (Box 5)
- Professional Series, 1914-2005 and undated, 84 boxes
  Consists of correspondence, clippings, articles, speeches, books, journals, chapters, drafts, proposals, notes, reports, scrapbooks, resumes, interviews, schedules, programs, pamphlets, administrative records, research materials, publications, promotional materials, and photographs that document Bogart's professional career. Series is divided into nine subseries: Biographical Materials Subseries; Conferences and Meetings Subseries; Correspondence Subseries; Early Career Subseries; Late Career Subseries; Newspaper Advertising Bureau (NAB) Subseries; Professional Service Subseries; Research Files Subseries; and Writings and Speeches Subseries.
  The Biographical Materials Subseries documents events and activities in Bogart's professional life, and includes clippings; interviews; correspondence; schedules; scrapbooks; and resumes.
  The Conferences and Meetings Subseries includes materials relating to conferences, seminars, meetings, and symposia in which Bogart participated. For materials relating to meetings and conferences in which Bogart gave a speech and a written record of the speech remains, see the Writings and Speeches Subseries. Arranged chronologically.
  The Correspondence Subseries consists of general and topical professional correspondence and is divided into five categories: Academic, Newspapers and print media, Organizations and businesses, People, and Miscellaneous. Arranged alphabetically within categories.
  The Early Career Subseries documents Bogart's professional career from 1951-1960, during which time Bogart worked as a Fulbright Research Fellow, and as a advertising and marketing researcher with Standard Oil Company of New Jersey; McCann-Erickson; and Revlon, Inc. The series includes the paper Bogart wrote as a Fulbright Fellow, Les Algérians en France; radio program audience research; and Revlon materials on quiz show fraud during the 1950s. Arranged topically and therein alphabetically.
  The Late Career Subseries documents Bogart's activities from 1989-2005 after he retired from the Newspaper Advertising Bureau. It includes materials related to Bogart's Gannett Center for Media Studies fellowship (later renamed the Freedom Forum Media Studies Center); newspaper consulting projects for the Freedom Forum; role as Director and Senior Consultant for Innovation International Media Consulting Group; and role as media expert in two trials in the 1990s, Chandler v. Jackson (Michael Jackson child molestation lawsuit) and Valenzuela v. Hughes Aircraft Company (TCE groundwater contamination lawsuit in Tuscon, Arizona). Slides of presentations given at the Freedom Forum Russian newspaper workshop and photographs of the trip are located in the Photographs and Slides Series. Presentation scripts are in Russian and English and slide text is in Russian. Videocassette tapes of media coverage of Michael Jackson and TCE groundwater contamination in Arizona are located in the Audiovisual Materials section. Arranged alphabetically.
  The Newspaper Advertising Bureau (NAB) Subseries documents Bogart's twenty-nine year executive career with the Newspaper Advertising Bureau (NAB), the advertising and marketing organization for the newspaper industry. Bogart began work with the NAB as Vice President of Marketing Planning and Research in 1960 and was promoted to Executive Vice President and General Manager in 1966. Bogart was the architect of many of the major research studies conducted during his tenure with the NAB. Bogart led two major research projects, the Newspaper Readership Project from 1977-1983 and the Future of Advertising Project from 1979-1988. The goal of the Newspaper Readership Project was to make recommendations to reverse declines in newspaper readership that begun in the 1920s and were threatening the vitality of the newspaper industry during the 1970s and 1980s. The Future of Advertising Project was formed shortly afterward to address newspapers' decline in national advertising revenues that began in the 1960s due largely to the rise of television. Recommendations from the Future of Advertising Project led to standardization in advertising formats and invoices across newspapers. This subseries is divided into three sections: General, Newspaper Readership Project, and Future of Advertising Project. General consists mainly of materials related to various research projects at the NAB. For slides of NAB presentations, see the Photographs & Slides Series. Speeches and presentations in this subseries report directly on the workings of the NAB; for all other speeches, see the Writings and Speeches Subseries. Arranged alphabetically within category except for speeches and meetings, which are arranged chronologically.
  The Professional Service Subseries documents Bogart's membership and service in professional organizations and clubs and on committees and advisory boards. Arranged alphabetically by organization.
  The Research Files Subseries consists of clippings, writings, and notes on various subjects that Bogart maintained for reference and as source material for his writings, speeches, and research. Arranged alphabetically by topic.